Guide to the University of Pittsburgh Van de Graaff Accelerator Records, 1947-1974 UA.90.8.29.1
ULS Archives & Special Collections
University of Pittsburgh Van de Graaff Accelerator Records
1947-1974
ULS Archives & Special Collections
University of Pittsburgh
UA.90.8.29.1
3.75 Linear Feet (3 boxes)
This collection consists of letters, diagrams, catalogs, and reports documenting the University of Pittsburgh's construction of an advanced cyclotron, called the Van de Graaff Accelerator, in the early 1960s.
History
A cyclotron is a powerful machine that has a wide array of applications for research in particle physics. It involves the use of a strong magnetic field to accelerate particles and resulting electric fields of varying strength to increase the speed at which they travel. In the early 1960s, the University of Pittsburgh was chosen to have one built on its campus that would be more powerful than others that had previously come before it. Pitt was able to secure over $1.6 million from the National Science Foundation and $1 million from the Sarah Mellon-Scaife Foundation to construct the building on campus.
Directed by Dr. James McGruer, construction began in November 1962 and was completed in March 1964. The first beams of protons were achieved in 1965 and the building itself was dedicated in 1966. Eventually, the building was renamed the Nuclear Physics Laboratory, although the building still goes by both names. Since its dedication, the accelerator has been an integral piece of equipment for both student and faculty research. Additions to the accelerator were made in the early 1970's to increase the power output of the machine.
Scope and Content Notes
This collection consists of letters, diagrams, catalogs, and reports documenting the University of Pittsburgh's construction of an advanced cyclotron in the early 1960s. These records involve correspondence written from contractors to the university, along with letters to and from different faculty involved with the project. Reports from the contractors and architects tasked with construction are present, along with the resulting blueprints and diagrams for the building itself. Records that span from the early discussions and proposals for the project to updates to the building after its completion are also found.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Transferred from the University of Pittsburgh Department of Physics and Astronomy in June 2015.
Pittsburgh (Pa.) -- Buildings, structures, etc.; Nuclear physics; University of Pittsburgh; University of Pittsburgh
- Skidmore, Owings & Merrill, I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  Chicago architectural and engineering firm Skidmore, Owings & Merrill (S.O.M.) was hired by the University of Pittsburgh to design and oversee construction of the Van de Graaff accelerator building beginning in 1961. This series includes correspondence from S.O.M. to the University of Pittsburgh, primarily the Physics department and the university architect, as well as contractors like the George A. Fuller Company and material suppliers.
  - Correspondence, August 23, 1961-May 17, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Weekly Construction Reports (Unfiled), November 1, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Recapitulation, November 10, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, May 18-July 11, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Recapitulation, July 2, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, July 16, 1962-February 12, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Changes to Drawings and Specifications, July 30-October 25, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, August 10-September 4, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Electrical Energy Analysis Report, August 24, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, September 7, 1962-June 6, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, September 7-October 5, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Material Submittals, October 5, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, October 15-November 30, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Transmittals, October 19, 1962-February 5, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, October 22-December 27, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, December 3, 1962-January 15, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Color and Material Schedule, December 27, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, January 2-February 8, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence, January 21-March 11, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Transmittals, February 11-April 29, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Revised Hardware Schedule, February 1, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence, February 11-March 30, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Notification of Change Order, February 15-May 7, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence, March 9-April 30, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Correspondence, April 1-June 11, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Notification of Change Order, April 16-May 23, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Transmittals, April 30, 1963-April 9, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Correspondence, May 1-June 13, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Notification of Building Change, May 21, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Correspondence, June 13-July 31, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Correspondence, June 17-July 9, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Recapitulation and Schedule, June 19, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Electrical Data Sheet, July 3, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Correspondence, July 1-December 3, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Notification of Change Order, July 8-August 22, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Correspondence, July 15-July 31, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Correspondence and Monthly Construction Reports, July 19, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Correspondence, August 1-31, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Correspondence, August 1-September 18, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Correspondence, September 3-30, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Notification of Change Order, September 5, 1963-February 10, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Correspondence, September 23-October 31, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Correspondence, October 2-28, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Hinge Structure Calculations, October 25, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Correspondence, October 30-December 27, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Correspondence, November 1-December 30, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Correspondence, January 2-February 6, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Correspondence, January 2-February 25,1964 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Correspondence, January 6-June 19, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Correspondence, February 10-April 7, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Notification of Change Order, February 24-August 19, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, March 2-April 30, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, April 15-May 28, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, May 4-August 25, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, June 1-July 23, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, August 4, 1964-June 7, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Heating and Ventilation Architectural and Mechanical Drawings (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Lasley K. Lacewell, II.
  Lasley K. Lacewell was an inspector in the Physical Plant office of the University of Pittsburgh assigned to serve as the university's field representative for the project. In that role, Lacewell oversew progress on the construction of the Van de Graaff accelerator building and managed the overall construction site. This series includes correspondence and reports documenting the day to day activities and progress of the building's construction.
  - Correspondence, November 14, 1962-April 30, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, May 1, 1963-January 29, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, February 3-September 4, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Weekly Update Report Correspondence, November 23, 1962-June 26, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Daily Construction Reports, October 19, 1962-January 25, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Daily Construction Reports, February 2-April 12, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Daily Construction Reports, April 15-June 28, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Daily Construction Reports, July 5-October 4, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Daily Construction Reports, October 14-December 27, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Daily Construction Reports, January 3-March 27, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Daily Construction Reports, April 3-June 12, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Daily Construction Reports, June 19-September 4, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Weekly Construction Reports, October 19, 1962-October 4, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Weekly Construction Reports, October 18, 1963-September 25, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Monthly Construction Reports, November 14, 1962-August 14, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- University of Pittsburgh, III.
  This series includes correspondence and memoranda from the University of Pittsburgh concerning the design and construction of the Van de Graaff accelerator building. Also included is the initial project proposal, as well as several subsequent proposals for equipment and upgrades. This series also contains drawings for several pieces of equipment utilized in the building and floor plans.
  - Cyclotron Correspondence, March 2, 1947-August 29, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Grants and Proposals (AEC, NSF), October 17, 1959-May 4, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Van de Graaff Accelerator Proposal, March 1, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Supplement to Van de Graaff Accelerator Proposal, November 1, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - David Halliday Correspondence, November 1, 1960-April 24, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Congressional and National Science Foundation Support Correspondence, May 2, 1961-April 2, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Memoranda, November 16, 1961-July 18, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Van de Graaff Expenses and Progress Reports, 1961-1962 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Van de Graaff Construction Organization Charts, February 12-September 23, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Correspondence and Dedication, April 3, 1962-May 6, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Correspondence, August 15, 1962-February 5, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Correspondence, October 26, 1962-July 8, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Correspondence, City of Pittsburgh, December 3, 1962-June 21, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Blasting Notices, December 14, 1962-January 7, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Correspondence, February 8-July 31, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Proposal for Equipment Grant, April 8, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Correspondence, City of Pittsburgh, June 28, 1963-May 29, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Correspondence, August 7-December 30, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Foreign Correspondence, September 13, 1963-January 2, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Correspondence, January 2-December 14, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Neutral Source Test Notes, January 9-10, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Correspondence, February 5-June 29, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Maintenance and Operating Instructions, May 15, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, July 2, 1964-March 5, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Door Design, January 15, 1962-October 28, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Van de Graaff Building Costs and Layouts, March 14-16, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Electrical, Heating, and Cooling Calculations, June 28-August 21, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Beam Drawings, November 12, 1962-February 29, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Electrical Information, November 21, 1962-February 17, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Architectural Designs, December 14, 1962-December 11, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Architectural Drawings, December 17, 1962-January 27, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Electric/Power Supply, December 21, 1962-March 14, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Van de Graaff Building Floor Plans, December 31, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Architectural and Mechanical Drawings, January 1-August 2, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Lockset Designs, January 7, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Architectural Designs, January 11-February 15, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Architectural Diagrams, January 23-March 27, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Final Approved Design, January 24, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Sheet Metal Designs, January 29-April 9, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Architectural and Mechanical Drawings, February 28-April 22, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Schedule of Yale Hardware, April 1, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Lighting Fixtures, September 11-16, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Job Memorandums (1-7), May 2, 1961-March 5, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Job Memorandums (8-14), April 2-September 10, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Instructions to Bidders (Sections 1-14), June 22, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Instructions to Bidders (Sections 15-39), June 22, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Instructions to Bidders (Sections 41-54), June 22, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Instructions to Bidders (Sections 55-70), June 22, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Instructions to Bidders (Sections 80-85), June 22, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Concrete Test Papers, December 4, 1962-February 14, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Concrete Test Papers, February 18-July 27, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Concrete Test Papers, July 27-October 21, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Concrete Test Papers, October 22, 1963-May 8, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Proposal for the Conversion of the Pittsburgh 18 MeV Van de Graaff into a 24 MeV EN-SUPER-FN Facility, March 1, 1971 (Box 3, Volume 1)
  - Proposal for Transfer of Army Model FN Tandem Van de Graaff Accelerator to University of Pittsburgh Nuclear Physics Laboratory, March 1, 1974 (Box 3, Volume 2)
- Contractors, IV.
  This series includes correspondence and progress reports from several contractors and equipment suppliers used during the construction of the Van de Graaff accelerator building. Also included are equipment catalogs from several companies considered during the bidding process.
  - George A. Fuller Company Correspondence, October 26, 1962-May 13, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - George A. Fuller Company Correspondence, May 14, 1963-August 13, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - George A. Fuller Company Progress Report, November 1, 1962-February 1, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - George A. Fuller Company Progress Report, April 1-July 1, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - George A. Fuller Company Monthly Progress Report, August 2-November 1, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - George A. Fuller Company Monthly Progress Report, December 5, 1963-March 2, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - George A. Fuller Company and Limbach Maintenance and Operating Instructions (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Limbach Correspondence, March 8-September 30, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Ackenheil & Associates Inc. Correspondence, November 2, 1962-May 15, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Ackenheil & Associates Inc. Architectural Diagrams, October 31, 1962-February 15, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Ackenheil & Associates Inc. Architectural Diagrams, March 4-April 2, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Tuttle & Bailey Grille and Diffuser Schedule, September 25, 1957-November 28, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Equipment Catalogs (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Equipment and Product Catalogs (Box 3, Folder 45)